One morning, I found baby chicks in my
grandparents' garden.
I was drinking coffee and I saw a little
Eurasian blue tit and it had something
in its mouth.
>> [music]
>> Then it flew into the birdhouse nailed
on the shed.
I got excited. So, when it left, I
walked to its little house
>> [music]
>> and looked inside.
It was dark.
But, I could just make out four, [music]
maybe five, light red, kind of
transparent baby chicks.
When they breathed, [music] they moved
with each other,
so weak that they were like wiggling,
not strong enough to fully keep [music]
themselves together,
stuck in this kind of loop of rapid
breathing movement.
I was excited with my new neighbors.
>> [music]
>> So, I sat back down and finished my
coffee.
But, the next morning, I heard a noise.
>> [music]
>> There was a great spotted woodpecker
picking the entrance of the birdhouse.
Huh.
What a stupid bird, I thought. [music]
The birdhouse comes from a factory,
mass-produced wood that's not meant to
rot outside. If it can get eaten by
maggots the first summer it's [music]
up, people would notice and complain.
The wood must be treated. I doubt
there's barely any insects inside.
But, then [music] it felt wrong.
I stepped outside and it flew away.
When I looked at the birdhouse,
>> [music]
>> it looked strange.
The woodpecker had pecked only around
the entrance,
>> [music]
>> as if it were trying to widen it.
For as long as there have been tits,
there have been those who have hunted
for them.
Passerines, [music]
also known as perching birds, are the
largest order of birds,
but they're one of the smallest in size.
[music]
The average passerine just doesn't weigh
that much, just a bit heavier than
hummingbirds and swifts.
>> [music]
>> Unlike, for example, chickens, baby
passerines are relatively weak. They sit
at an extreme end of the bird
development spectrum.
Precocial birds are self-sufficient soon
after birth.
The chicks hatch with eyes open, have
[music] downy insulation, and the
ability to walk or swim practically
immediately.
Passerines, however, are altricial.
A blue tit female cannot store big
energy reserves for serious egg
development.
They need to shift the development
post-hatching.
The whole clutch may or may not exceed
her body mass, but because production is
spread across 14 days, and she can
supply food later,
>> [music]
>> she never has to carry all that mass all
at once.
But, it does mean that her chicks leave
the egg blind, [music] featherless,
immobile, and like humans, helpless.
But, what they trade for early
self-reliance, they gain in [music]
rapid growth.
It doesn't take long for a passerine
chick to reach its full adult mass,
assuming [music] it lives that long.
Because before they're self-sufficient,
the passerine's chicks' reliance [music]
on their parents can attract unwanted
attention.
They need a constant supply of food,
so they come with noisy cries demanding
[music]
attention.
And that can attract more than mom.
Passerines [music] invest heavily in
guarding their young through
constructing entirely new external nests
that will be used from initial hatch to
full development.
The southern masked weaver, for example,
gathers fresh blades of grass, and the
males knot hundreds of strands into a
fully enclosed cradle [music] that can
hang a meter below a branch.
The Baltimore oriole crochets a deep
flexible pouch that swings [music] in a
windproof hammock.
The Eurasian tree creeper finds tiny
[music] crevices in bark and hides its
young behind flaps of wood.
The Cape Eurasian penduline [music] tit
will build a nest with a dummy doorway.
A false entrance gives the impression to
predators that there is no high-calorie
brood to be found.
And the Eurasian blue tit primarily
[music] constructs its nests in tree
cavities, walls, or nest boxes.
This protects them from many predators,
but it's not perfect.
Weasels can demolish an entire tit
brood.
The forest dormouse will kill the young
and regularly kill the adults as well.
A tit clutch, which can be as high as 12
eggs, can be an instant high-protein
meal,
almost 1 g per chick.
But there's one predator that destroys
tit broods like none other.
In a box colony in South Sweden, nearly
half of all predation events [music] on
tit nest boxes were caused by it.
It locates boxes with 5 to 14-day-old
chicks by honing in on begging calls.
It will tap, pause, listen, and resume
as the chicks give away their position.
Every once in a while, it came back.
It pecked and got my attention.
So, I ran outside and I shooed it away.
It was irrational, I know.
This was nature.
If anything, the woodpecker was probably
more rare in Amsterdam than any Eurasian
tit.
Maybe I should have helped widen the
entrance.
But still, there was something about it
that felt wrong.
Odoo is a European company that makes an
all-in-one business software.
More than 45 integrated apps in one
platform.
And the one to start with is their
e-commerce app.
You describe your store and its AI
builds the whole site for you. Pages,
colors, products.
You add an item with your name, a price,
and a photo, and you've already got wish
lists, reviews, and search.
Stripe and Ingenico handle the payments.
DHL and SendCloud handle the shipping.
Because it's Odoo, every sale links
straight to your accounting and your
inventory. So, you have one source of
truth from your very first order. Little
disconnects like that really add up
costs for small medium businesses.
And luckily, Odoo's first app is free
for life with unlimited hosting,
support, and a free custom domain for a
year. The full suite is 19.90 euros a
month. Start your store at the link in
the description.
When woodpeckers consume baby chicks,
they can focus on the brain.
The Gila woodpecker, a medium-sized
woodpecker of the desert regions of the
southwestern United States and western
Mexico, has been documented cracking
into baby bird [music] skulls
and eating drinking their brains,
a good source of water in the hot
environment.
A chick brain is about 50% lipid by dry
weight.
Following the same logic as a fruit with
a tough skin, the woodpecker will go for
the soft pulpy inside.
Bone formation of the skull takes many
days.
Before then, the brain is protected like
any other egg,
and it can be a great source of protein
and lipids.
It takes seconds to access it.
Muscle or fat requires ripping skin and
tendons, many more pecks. [music]
Every gram of the brain contains much
more fat than muscle,
and it's already pre-emulsified, so it's
easy to swallow.
The brain is also a tissue that is
simultaneously energy dense, nutrient
rich, and easily accessible.
Although insects and seeds may still be
a better choice per peck, the brain is
among the richest wet foods available in
early spring,
which makes it a prime target.
The woodpecker couldn't fit through the
entrance, so it had to peck to access
the chicks inside.
But there was no point in pecking the
entire birdhouse open before it could
fit its entire body through.
So instead, it slowly sculpted [music]
it just wide enough.
Just enough so that it could reach the
chicks.
>> [music]
>> But, to do that, the woodpecker had to
test. No point drilling more than what
was necessary.
And something about that felt so wrong.
The chicks would hear the noise of
something outside. They'd open their
mouths expecting their mom, and the hole
of the birdhouse would turn black.
And something above them would reach for
them.
But, it didn't It just couldn't quite
yet.
>> [music]
>> It snapped, maybe tested its tongue,
and then it would pull back. Light and
the noise of the outside world would
fill the room again.
And the pecking resumed.
Maybe once in a while they'd get a
glimpse of this strange
different animal right outside the hole.
And every time it came back, it would
just get a little bit closer.
So, I went outside, and I scared it
away.
But, the next day, it came again.
I swear it perched on the stick for just
a moment.
It looked at me, and I looked back.
Then it reached its body inside the
house, and ripped a chick out right in
front of my eyes.
And then it flew away.
That was the last straw.
Intuitively, it makes sense why the
woodpecker is especially good at hunting
chicks in birdhouses.
It bores its own nest into existence, so
it can use the same skills to break into
the nests of others.
They're able to smash their head into
wood 20 times a second.
The reason a woodpecker can bore 20
times a second without serious brain
damage is because of the size of their
brains.
Like dropping a ping-pong ball versus a
bowling ball on a tile floor, the
woodpecker can smash its head into a
tree and come out with minimal brain
damage.
There's this popular image out there
that the tongue of the woodpecker is
this kind of unique shock absorber
[music] because it wraps around its
head, but this is just objectively uh
untrue. It's false.
Hummingbirds, which don't bore, also
have a tongue that wraps around their
head.
Their tongues are just extra long in
order to get to hard-to-reach places.
The woodpecker uses its extra long
tongue to probe bark for larva. Even if
it couldn't grab the chicks with its
beak, for some time, it could probably
still touch them from like 4 cm away.
What a beautiful thing, Mother Nature.
I'd already failed a mother once.
I wasn't going to fail her a second
time.
And when she flew back to her nest, I
could swear that she peeped her head out
quicker than she normally did. As though
she was registering that one was gone.
When she left, I went with my phone to
the hole to check how many chicks were
left.
There were still at least three.
I had to do something.
I had to come up with a permanent
solution.
So, I told my pension grandfather about
what happened.
With too much time on his hands and
looking for any problem to solve,
besides how to handle being alone with
the silence of his own thoughts and
retirement, he was eager.
So, together we cut five old yogurt
containers into a circle with a hole.
When I need to change a light bulb, I
call my entire family.
We glued them together and made them
into a thick puck.
On the birdhouse, we nailed them onto
the entrance.
It stressed out the chicks, but this
would be the last of the pecking they'd
ever hear.
So, we stood by the window and waited
for Mom to come back and see if she
could fit.
>> [music]
>> She could.
Plastic was a bit more resistant to
damage than wood. It would dent rather
than fracture. The weird material might
be enough to make the woodpecker feel
strange about continuing.
So, we waited.
>> [music]
>> And when the woodpecker came back, it
stopped.
It seemed confused.
It waited for some time and then flew
away.
Success.
This was one of the most meaningful
things I'd ever done in my entire life.
So, I turned back to my computer and I
felt better than normal with that
achievement behind my back.
I learned to forget to look at the
birdhouse.
On the third day, the plastic was still
intact.
I smiled and kept going to university
and I forgot.
But, a week or so later, I took my bike
through the back entrance
and I saw something strange.
On the left side of the birdhouse, where
a wood wall used to be, was now a hole.
I checked inside the house with a
flashlight on my phone.
>> [music]
>> There were no baby chicks in my
grandparents' garden.